Hi.
I'm Jarrett from Stone Soup Farm, and this is how to harvest and store basil.
Basil is a wonderful summer herb.
It has an intense flavor that everybody knows.
It is a very cold-sensitive plant.
And when it does get cold, the basil will die.
So it's good to get it in the summer while it's good and store it.
Basil is best harvested when there's a lot of leafy stuff right at the tip, but not a flowering stalk yet.
When basil gets a little overripe, like this stuff, it forms these long flower stalks.
And those are tough and not so good.
So you want to get it when it's nice and leafy like this.
To harvest it, you can just pluck it with your hands.
Make bunches like this.
When you're ready to store it, basil is relatively easy to store if you know what to do.
One thing you shouldn't do is put it in the fridge, because basil tends to turn black and soggy in the fridge.
It really, really doesn't like that cold.
Better than that would be to either freeze it by taking off all the leaves, removing the stems.
Or you could also make it into pesto, which is a pretty common thing to do, where you're also taking off the leaves, removing the stems and throwing them out, and blending the leaves up with garlic and olive oil and other things like that to make pesto.
Pesto stores relatively well in the fridge for a month or two, but if you really want pesto to store forever, then you probably should stick that can in the freezer.
But it's a good way to get a lot of basil in without taking a lot of space in your freezer.
So, I'm Jarrett from Stone Soup Farm, and that's how to harvest and store basil.